As a lover of human anatomy,
كمُحبة لعلم التشريح البشري،
I'm so excited that we're finally putting our bodies at the center of focus.
أنا سعيدة جدا بأننا أخيرا نضع أجسادنا في مركز الإهتمام.
Through practices such as preventive medicine,
من خلال ممارسات مثل الطب الوقائي،
patient empowerment
تمكين المرضى
and self-monitoring --
والرصد الذاتي
down to now obsessing over every single step we take in a day.
وحتى التوجس حاليا حول كل خطوة نخطوها في اليوم.
All of this works to promote
كل هذا يعمل لترويج
a healthy connection between ourselves and our bodies.
تواصل صحَي بيننا وبين أجسادنا.
Despite all this focus on the healthy self,
رغم كل التركيز على الذات الصحية،
general public knowledge of the anatomical self is lacking.
المعرفة العامة الشائعة عن الذات التشريحية قليلة.
Many people don't know the location of their vital organs,
لا يعرف الكثير من الأشخاص مواقع أعضائهم الحيوية،
or even how they function.
أو حتى كيف تعمل.
And that's because human anatomy
وذلك لأن علم التشريح البشري
is a difficult and time-intensive subject to learn.
مادة صعبة وتستغرق وقتا طويلا لتعلَمها.
How many of you here made it through anatomy?
كم منكم هنا أكمل تعلم علم التشريح؟
Wow, good --
واو، جيد ..
most of you are in medicine.
معظمكم من المختصين بالطب.
I, like you, spent countless hours memorizing hundreds of structures.
أنا، مثلكم، قضيت ساعات لا تحصى في حفظ مئات التراكيب.
Something no student of anatomy could do without the help of visuals.
أمر لا يمكن لأيَ طالب تشريح عمله بدون مساعدة الوسائل البصرية.
Because at the end of the day,
لأنه في نهاية اليوم،
whether you remember every little structure or not,
سواء تذكرت كل تركيب صغير أم لم تفعل،
these medical illustrations are what makes studying anatomy so intriguing.
هذه الرسوم التوضيحية الطبية هي ما يجعل دراسة التشريح مثيرة جدا.
In looking at them,
من خلال النظر إليها،
we're actually viewing a manual of our very selves.
نحن في الواقع نشاهد دليلا توضيحيا لأنفسنا.
But what happens when we're done studying?
ولكن ماذا يحدث عندما ننتهي من الدراسة؟
These beautiful illustrations are then shut back
تعاد هذه الرسومات التوضيحية الجميلة لتُحبس
into the pages of a medical textbook,
داخل صفحات كتب الطب،
or an app,
أو في تطبيق،
referenced only when needed.
للرجوع إليها عند الحاجة فقط.
And for the public,
وبالنسبة للعامة،
medical illustrations may only be encountered passively
يمكن مشاهدة الرسومات التوضيحية الطبية بشكل سلبي فقط
on the walls of a doctor's office.
على جدران مكتب الطبيب.
From the beginnings of modern medicine,
منذ بدايات الطب الحديث،
medical illustration,
الرسومات التوضيحية الطبية،
and therefore anatomy,
وبالتالي علم التشريح،
have existed primarily within the realm of medical education.
تواجدت بشكل أساسي داخل حقل التعليم الطبي.
Yet there's something fascinating happening right now.
لكن هناك أمر مدهش يحدث الآن.
Artists are breaking anatomy out of the confines of the medical world
الفنانون يُخرجون علم التشريح من حدود العالم الطبي
and are thrusting it into the public space.
ويدفعون به إلى الفضاء العام.
For the past nine years, I have been cataloguing and sharing
خلال السنوات التسع الماضية، كنت أفهرس وأشارك
this rise in anatomical art with the public --
هذا التصاعد في الفن التشريحي بين العامة
all from my perspective as a medical illustrator.
من خلال منظوري كفنانة رسوم توضيحية طبية.
But before I get into showing you how artists are reclaiming anatomy today,
لكن قبل أن أُريكم كيف يقوم الفنانون باستعادة التشريح اليوم،
it's important to understand how art influenced anatomy in the past.
من المهم أن نفهم كيف أثَر الفن على علم التشريح في الماضي.
Now, anatomy is by its very nature a visual science,
الآن، التشريح بطبيعته هو علم بصري،
and the first anatomists to understand this lived during the Renaissance.
وأول من فهم ذلك من علماء التشريح عاشوا في عصر النهضة.
They relied on artists
اعتمدوا على الفنانين
to help advertise their discoveries to their peers in the public.
لمساعدتهم في الإعلان عن اكتشافاتهم لنظرائهم بين العامة.
And this drive to not only teach but also to entertain
وهذه النزعة لعدم الإكتفاء بالتعليم ولكن للتسلية أيضا
resulted in some of the strangest anatomical illustrations.
تسببت في ظهور بعض أغرب الرسومات التشريحية.
Anatomy was caught in a struggle between science, art and culture
كان علم التشريح عالقا في صراع بين العلم والفن والثقافة
that lasted for over 500 years.
استمر لأكثر من 500 عام.
Artists rendered dissected cadavers as alive,
قدَم الفنانون جثث التشريح كما لو كانت حيَة،
posed in these humorous anatomical stripteases.
معروضة في أوضاع تعرَي تشريحية هزلية.
Imagine seeing that in your textbooks today.
تصوَروا رؤية ذلك في كتبكم اليوم.
They also showed them as very much dead --
كما أظهروهم كموتى أيضا
unwillingly stripped of their skin.
مجرّدين من جلودهم دون موافقتهم.
Disembodied limbs were often posed in literal still lives.
أطراف منتزعة كانت تعرض في كثير من الأحيان في حياة ساكنة حرفيا.
And some illustrations even included pop culture references.
حتى أن بعض الرسومات التوضيحية كانت تحتوي على اشارات للثقافة الشعبية.
This is Clara,
هذه (كلارا).
a famous rhinoceros that was traveling Europe in the mid-1700s,
أنثى وحيد قرن شهيرة كانت تسافر عبر أوروبا في منتصف القرن الثامن عشر،
at a time when seeing a rhino was an exciting rarity.
في وقت كانت فيه رؤية وحيد القرن أمرا نادرا ومثيرا.
Including her in this illustration was akin to celebrity sponsorship today.
وضعها في هذا الرسم التوضيحي كان مشابها لرعاية المشاهير اليوم.
The introduction of color
بداية استخدام الألوان
then brought a whole new depth and clarity to anatomy
أظهرت بعد ذلك عُمقا جديدا ووضوحا لعلم التشريح
that made it stunning.
مما جعله مذهلا.
By the early 20th century,
في بدايات القرن العشرين،
the perfect balance of science and art had finally been struck
التوازن المثالي بين العلم والفن صُدم أخيرا
with the emergence of medical illustrators.
بظهور فناني الرسوم التوضيحية الطبية.
They created a universal representation of anatomy --
لقد خلقوا تمثيلا عالميا لعلم التشريح
something that was neither alive nor dead,
شيء لم يكن حياً أو ميتاً،
that was free from those influences of artistic culture.
حرَ من تأثيرات الثقافة الفنية تلك.
And this focus on no-frills accuracy
وهذا التركيز على الدقة الغير مبهرجة
was precisely for the benefit of medical education.
كان مفيدا بالتحديد للتعليم الطبي.
And this is what we get to study from today.
وهذا ما يمكننا أن ندرس منه اليوم.
But why is it that medical illustration --
ولكن لماذا تقوم تلك الرسوم التوضيحية،
both past and present --
في كل من الماضي والحاضر،
captures our imaginations?
بأسر خيالنا؟
Now, we are innately tuned into the beauty of the human body.
الأن، نحن موجهون بالفطرة إلى جمال الجسد البشري.
And medical illustration is still art.
والرسومات التوضيحية الطبية لا تزال فناً.
Nothing can elicit an emotional response --
لا شيء يمكنه استخلاص استجابة عاطفية،
from joy to complete disgust --
من الفرح إلى الإشمئزاز التام،
more than the human body.
أكثر من الجسد البشري.
And today,
واليوم،
artists armed with that emotion,
الفنانون المسلَحون بتلك العواطف،
are grasping anatomy from the medical world,
يجتذبون علم التشريح من عالم الطب،
and are reinvigorating it through art in the most imaginative ways.
ويعيدون إحياءه من خلال الفن بأكثر الطرق خياليةً.
A perfect example of this is Spanish contemporary artist Fernando Vicente.
أحد أفضل الأمثلة على ذلك الفنان الإسباني المعاصر (فيرناندو فيسينتى).
He takes 19th century anatomical illustrations of the male body
يقوم بأخذ رسوم توضيحية تشريحية من القرن التاسع عشر للجسد الذكري
and envelops them in a female sensuality.
وتغليفها بشهوانية أنثوية.
The women in his paintings taunt us to view beyond their surface anatomy,
النساء في لوحاته تستفزَنا لننظر إلى ما هو أبعد من تشريحهن السطحي،
thereby introducing a strong femininity
مما يظهر أنثوية قوية.
that was previously lacking in the history of anatomical representation.
لم تكن موجودة سابقا في تاريخ التمثيل التشريحي.
Artistry can also be seen in the repair and recovery of the human body.
يمكن رؤية البراعة الفنية أيضا في إصلاح وإستعادة الجسد البشري.
This is an X-ray of a woman who fractured and dislocated her ankle
هذه أشعة سينية لإمرأة قامت بكسر وخلع كاحلها
in a roller-skating accident.
في حادث تزلج بأحذية العجلات.
As a tribute to her trauma,
كتحية لإصابتها،
she commissioned Montreal-based architect Federico Carbajal
قامت بتكليف المهندس المعماري (فيديريكو كارباهال) المقيم في (مونتريال)
to construct a wire sculpture of her damaged lower leg.
بصنع منحوتة من الأسلاك تمثَل أسفل ساقها المصاب.
Now, notice those bright red screws magnified in the sculpture.
الآن، لاحظوا تلك البراغي الحمراء الزاهية مكبَرة في المنحوتة.
These are the actual surgical screws used in reconstructing her ankle.
هذه هي البراغي الجراحية الحقيقية التي استخدمت لإعادة بناء كاحلها.
It's medical hardware that's been repurposed as art.
إنها معدات طبية أُعيد توظيفها كقطع فنية.
People often ask me how I choose the art that I showcase online
يسألني الناس كثيرا عن كيفية اختياري للأعمال الفنية التي أعرضها على الإنترنت
or feature in gallery shows.
أو في صالات العرض.
And for me it's a balance between the technique
وبالنسبة لي هو توازن ما بين التقنية
and a concept that pushes the boundaries of anatomy as a way to know thyself,
والفكرة التي تدفع بحواجز علم التشريح كوسيلة لمعرفة نفسك،
which is why the work of Michael Reedy struck me.
وهو السبب الذي أذهلني به عمل (مايكل ريدي).
His serious figure drawings are often layered in elements of humor.
رسوماته للأشكال الجديَة كثيرا ما تُصنع بشكل طبقات بطريقة فكاهية.
For instance, take a look at her face.
على سبيل المثال، انظروا إلى وجهها.
Notice those red marks.
لاحظوا تلك العلامات الحمراء.
Michael manifests the consuming insecurity of a skin condition
يقوم (مايكل) بتجسيد انعدام الأمان الكاسح المتعلق بحالة الجلد
as these maniacal cartoon monsters
بصورة هذه الوحوش الكرتونية المجنونة
annoying and out of control in the background.
مزعجة وخارجة عن السيطرة في الخلفية.
On the mirrored figure,
في الشكل المعكوس،
he renders the full anatomy
يقوم برسم التشريح كاملا
and covers it in glitter,
وتغطيته بمادة لامعة،
making it look like candy.
مما يجعله يبدو كالحلوى.
By doing this,
بفعل هذا،
Michael downplays the common perception of anatomy
يقلل (مايكل) من أهمية التصوَر الشائع عن علم الشريح
so closely tied to just disease and death.
المرتبط ارتباطا وثيقا بالمرض والموت فقط.
Now, this next concept might not make much sense,
الآن الفكرة القادمة قد لا تكون منطقية جدا،
but human anatomy is no longer limited to humans.
لكن علم التشريح البشري لم يعد محدودا بالبشر.
When you were a child,
عندما كنتَ طفلا،
did you ever wish that your toys could come to life?
هل حدث وتمنيت أن تدبَ الحياة في ألعابك؟
Well, Jason Freeny makes those dreams come true
حسنا، (جايسون فريني) يقوم بتحقيق تلك الأحلام
with his magical toy dissections.
عن طريق تشريحه السحري للألعاب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
One might think that this would bring a morbid edge
قد يظن البعض أن هذا قد يجلب إضافة مزعجة
to one's innocent childhood characters,
إلى شخصيات الطفولة البريئة،
but Jason says of his dissections,
لكن (جايسون) يقول عن تشريحاته،
"One thing I've never seen in a child's reaction to my work is fear."
"أمر واحد لم أره في ردة فعل الأطفال تجاه عملي هو الخوف."
It's always wonder,
هناك دائما التعجب،
amazement
الإندهاش
and wanting to explore.
والرغبة في الإستكشاف.
Fear of anatomy and guts is a learned reaction.
الخوف من التشريح والأحشاء هو رد فعل مكتسب.
This anatomization also extends to politically and socially charged objects.
أسلوب التشريح هذا يمتد أيضا إلى الأمور المتعلقة بالمجتمع والسياسة.
In Noah Scalin's "Anatomy of War,"
في كتاب (نوح سكالين) (Anatomy of War)
we see a gun dissected to reveal human organs.
نرى سلاحاً تم تشريحه ليُظهر أعضاءاً بشرية.
But if you look closely,
ولكن إن نظرتم عن قرب،
you'll notice that it lacks a brain.
سترون أنه لا يحتوى على دماغ.
And if you keep looking, you might also notice
وإن تابعتم النظر، ربما لاحظتم أيضا
that Noah has so thoughtfully placed the rectum
أن (نوح) قد وضع المستقيم بشكل مدروس
at the business end of that gun barrel.
في النهاية العملية من ماسورة السلاح.
Now, this next artist I've been following for many years,
الآن لقد تابعت الفنان التالي لسنوات عدَة،
watching him excite the public about anatomy.
ورأيته يثير حماس العامة حول التشريح.
Danny Quirk is a young artist
(داني كويرك) هو فنان شاب
who paints his subjects in the process of self-dissection.
وهو يرسم موضوعاته كجزء من عملية التشريح الذاتي.
He bends the rules of medical illustration
إنه يحطم قواعد الرسوم التوضيحية الطبية
by inserting a very dramatic light and shadow.
عن طريق إدخال الضوء والظلال بشكل مسرحي جدا.
And this creates a 3-D illusion
وهذ يخلق وهماً بأن الصورة ثلاثية الأبعاد
that lends itself very well to painting directly on the human skin.
مما يفسح المجال بشكل جيد جدا للرسم مباشرة على الجلد البشري.
Danny makes it look as if a person's skin has actually been removed.
(داني) يجعل الأمر كما لو أن جلد الشخص قد تمت إزالته فعليا.
And this effect --
وهذا التأثير،
also cool and tattoo-like --
يبدو رائعا أيضا ومشابها للوشم،
easily transitions into a medical illustration.
يمكن نقله بسهولة إلى الرسومات التوضيحية الطبية.
Now Danny is currently traveling the world,
(داني) يسافر حول العالم حالياً،
teaching anatomy to the public via his body paintings,
ويقوم بتدريس التشريح البشري للعامة عبر رسوماته،
which is why it was so shocking to find out
ولهذا كان من الصادم جدا إكتشاف
that he was rejected from medical illustration programs.
أنه قد تم رفضه من قبل برامج الرسم التوضيحي الطبي.
But he's doing just fine.
لكنه يدبَر أموره بشكل جيد.
Then there are artists
ثم هناك فنانون
who are extracting anatomy from both the medical world and the art world
يستخلصون التشريح من كلٍ من العالم الطبي وعالم الفن
and are placing it directly on the streets.
ويضعونه في الشوارع مباشرة.
London-based SHOK-1 paints giant X-rays of pop culture icons.
(شوك-1) من (لندن) يرسم صورا عملاقة للأشعة السينية لرموز ثقافة البوب.
His X-rays show how culture can come to have an anatomy of its own,
صور الأشعة السينية الخاصة به تُظهر كيف يمكن أن يكون للثقافة تشريحها الخاص.
and conversely how culture can become part of the anatomy of a person.
وفي المقابل كيف يمكن أن تصبح الثقافة جزءا من تشريح الشخص.
You come to admire his work
سوف تُعجبون بعمله
because reproducing X-rays by hand, let alone with spray paint,
لأن إنتاج أشعة سينية باليد، ناهيك عن استخدام رذاذ الطلاء،
is extremely difficult.
هو أمر صعب جدا.
But then again this is a street artist,
ولكن مرة أخرى هذا فنان شوارع،
who also happens to hold a degree in applied chemistry.
والذي يصادف أنه يحمل درجة علمية في الكيمياء التطبيقية.
Nychos, an Austrian street artist,
(نايكوس)، فنان شوارع أسترالي،
takes the term "exploded view" to a whole new level,
يأخذ مصطلح "المنظر المتفجر" إلى مستوى جديد تماما،
splattering human and animal dissections on walls all over the world.
ناثرا تشريحات البشر والحيوانات على الجدران في جميع أنحاء العالم.
Influenced by comics and heavy metal,
متأثرا بالكتب المصوَرة وموسيقى (هيفي ميتال)،
Nychos inserts a very youthful and enticing energy into anatomy
يقوم (نايكوس) بإضافة طاقة شابة وجذابة إلى علم التشريح
that I just love.
والتي أُحبها كثيرا.
Street artists believe that art belongs to the public.
فنانو الشوارع يؤمنون بأن الفن ينتمي إلى العامة.
And this street anatomy is so captivating
والتشريح في الشوارع هذا أخَاذ جدا
because it is the furthest removed from the medical world.
لأنه الأكثر بُعدا عن عالم الطب.
It forces you to look at it,
إنه يجبرك على النظر إليه،
and confront your own perceptions about anatomy,
ومواجهة منظورك الخاص عن التشريح.
whether you find it beautiful,
سواء كنت تجده جميلا،
gross,
مقرفا،
morbid
مزعجا،
or awe-inspiring, like I do.
أو مذهلا، كما أجده أنا.
That it elicits these responses at all
كونه يسبب ردود الفعل هذه
is due to our intimate and often changing relationship with it.
هو بسبب علاقتنا الحميمة والمتغيرة كثيرا به.
All of the artists that I showed you here today
جميع الفنانين الذين أريتكم إياهم اليوم
referenced medical illustrations for their art.
استخدموا الرسوم التوضيحية الطبية كمرجع لفنَهم.
But for them,
ولكن بالنسبة لهم،
anatomy isn't just something to memorize,
علم التشريح ليس فقط شيئا تحفظه،
but a base from which to understand the human body on a meaningful level;
ولكنه قاعدة يمكن أن نفهم منها الجسد البشري على مستوى ذو معنى؛
to depict it in ways that we can relate,
أن نصوَره بطُرق يمكن أن نفهمها،
whether it be through cartoons,
سواء عن طريق الرسوم الكرتونية،
body painting
لوحات الجسد
or street art.
أو فن الشوارع.
Anatomical art has the power
الفن التشريحي يملك من القوة
to reach far beyond the pages of a medical textbook,
ما يمكنَه من الوصول إلى ما هو أبعد من الكتب الدراسية الطبية،
to ignite an excitement in the public,
ليشعل اهتمام العامة،
and reinvigorate an enthusiasm in the medical world,
ويعيد تنشيط الحماس في عالم الطب،
ultimately connecting our innermost selves with our bodies through art.
ليربط أخيرا ذواتنا الداخلية بأجسادنا من خلال الفن.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)